welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where equal hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
okay all right everyone welcome to the
stoah I'm the Stewart of the stoah Peter
Lindbergh some of you may know I run the
stoic group here in Toronto Canada and
obviously we can't meet right now in to
do the situation so I decided to launch
the stoah which I'm a viewing as not
just a space to talk and practice about
stoicism but a place to for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the nice edge of this moment and I'm
bringing in a lot of people to do
practice different exercises and to give
talks and today we have a special guest
my friend Greg Sadler
Greg is a a PPA certified philosophical
counselor is the editor of stoicism
today and he's the president of reason
IO which is an organization that puts
velocity into practice and he's gonna
give a talk today on stoic fortitude and
it's gonna be about 20 minutes and then
we're gonna open up to questions or QA
and if you have a question for Greg just
write it in the chat box and I'll ask
you to unmute yourself and you can read
it or if you want me to read it on your
behalf
just indicate that in the chat that
being said I'll hand it over to Greg
thanks Peter and thanks for the
invitation to come into this virtual
space and talk about these things so I
am going to talk about fortitude or the
the virtue of courage but I'm also
talking quite a bit about failure and
failings and when when Peter approached
me about what topic I might want to talk
about that's what came to mind right
away because I think that we don't we
don't talk about it enough in terms of
stoicism I know in our local group we we
do every once in a while I'll bring up
where we went wrong and then we analyze
it but there's you know it's not it's
not something that people are often
happy to discuss and it's really
important because any mode of
intentional living and constants and
this one of those there's gonna be a lot
of failings and a lot
failures so stoicism helps us to
understand those and to wean ourselves
away from dysfunctional approaches to
the inevitable failures that we have and
the reason why I pick fortitude wasn't
just because you know the alliteration
the nice F sounds or something like that
it's because if we if we look at what
the Stoics actually said about that
virtue fortitude or courage it's broader
than just dealing with fears and it
really does have some some resources
there to help us deal with the
inevitable failures that we right into
so this is gonna be kind of restricted
in scope there's so much that could be
said about this I think one could
actually write a small book about it
we're gonna talk and I've already used
up probably a minute of the time this is
gonna get on some some key points so you
know I talked about why this this issue
and I'll start by talking about a a
failing of mine that's also culminated
in several failures for all of you know
if you're not involved in academia all
of your still you know quite aware that
everything has had to go online and that
takes a lot of work and a lot of thought
from this and I've been teaching online
for eight years now so you know when we
first got quarantined until they we're
gonna extend Spring Break you better
start shifting the classes online that
first weekend I thought oh this is a
perfect opportunity I can like get a lot
of this work done right away and then I
found myself as many of you probably
have as well and this is a topic we
could talk about as well at the end you
know feeling kind of unmotivated feeling
kind of kind of blue and sad and not
getting the things done that I I said I
would and that's you know that's both a
failure but it's also a failing and I'll
talk about the difference between those
in a bit because it's something that I
you know often do more often than I'd
like I create this great Google Calendar
full of things that I'm gonna do and
then I don't actually get to them and
then I
revise it and take stock of the fact
that the work didn't get done and who
does it affect well it affects my
students and it's not like I left them
in the lurch but I wanted to do all
these different things that would use
their transition and keep them from
feeling anxious and I got maybe half of
them done you know on the scale that I
wanted so you know that's sort of a
classic instance I have some duties
towards these people that I have
response with I know what the right
thing is to do and yet I find myself not
getting all of the right thing done and
I think many of you can bring up similar
instances in in your own just the last
couple weeks the quarantine and the
staying at home and all the anxieties
about koban 19 and the situation that
we're in I think makes this even more
important to talk about because as we
put more stress on the systems that we
live in and we put more stress upon
ourselves we're going to make more
mistakes we're going to shift into
unhealthy ways of looking at things so
let's talk about failings and failures
we often use these words synonymously as
if they're the same thing
and I'm not saying that we have to be
you know grammar police or anything like
that about this but it is useful to make
a distinction we often fail at things
and we do so in determinate ways within
situations that's a failure and it could
be minor it could be I forgot to take
the dog out and so the dog is is upset
you know and maybe has an accident or
something like that and then has to be
cleaned up and you know inconveniences
people or it could be a really big thing
like I didn't check into my classes all
week and my students are wondering where
where is this guy what are we going to
do and and there's all sorts of
possibilities and then when we realize
that we've failed sometimes we realize
that there's something more going
we have failings there's there's things
about ourselves that aren't what we'd
like them to be and you know our society
is very good at giving us all sorts of
sometimes correct and very often
incorrect information about what our
failings would be you might think about
the fashion industry and how it pushes a
certain not just you know coiffeur and
and you know set of clothes that should
change every season but body types and
what we ought to be investing our time
and attention into those those can make
us think that we're fail that we're
failing when we're not really doing so
so we can talk about that as well we
also see failings and failures in other
people and one of the things I think we
can be on guard from the beginning
against is interpreting failures on
people's part as automatically
signifying failings on their part so if
I you know neglect an email for a while
and don't respond to it right away
that doesn't mean that that that failure
is automatically because of a failing
with me and not wanting to address
people or being disrespectful or
anything along those lines but you know
we have to be on guard against that
because that's a natural tendency to
read those things into other people's
behavior so in any as I was saying in
any path of intentional living and
personal development we really want to
expect to fail very often when we're
starting it and you know I know just
looking at the list of people here some
of you have been practicing stoicism for
quite a long time and even then all of
those who can't then you can weigh in
and say yeah we keep on failing as well
but when you're first embracing some
stomach principles and practices you're
gonna fail all the time and you know
that's just part of the course it's just
like learning a musical instrument or
going to the gym and starting a new
exercise routine you know
it makes sense that that would happen
and so you know dealing with failure
productively is going to be very
important for us and you know we can
think about some of the ways in which we
fail and I came up with a list here I'm
just gonna like hit on some of the
general ways right some of them are
cognitive we get mixed up in what we
think or assume or we have incorrect
ideas about things like mixing up what's
in our control and what's what's not in
our control we make mistaken inferences
we follow out automatic lines of thought
processes or lines of reasoning that are
mistaken sometimes we actually just sort
of make a mistake almost like you know
in mathematics would be lined up with
the wrong number at the end we're not
quite sure how we got there we get the
wrong results but we do that with our
reasoning as well but we also have
effective ways in which we fail and this
is where I think service ISM can be
really helpful in telling us what we
what we want to desire what we ought to
be averse to right
we often desire the wrong things or are
averse to the wrong things or too much
too little we direct our emotions
towards the wrong objects sometimes we
act on them in ways that are not helpful
for us or for others and we often do
realize if we've been thinking about
ourselves in examining ourselves which
is part of stoicism that we we should
feel something better or different but
don't then we feel that as a failure
right on our on our part there's also a
volitional modalities we we sometimes
choose the wrong things or commit to the
wrong things the bad instead of the good
and then afterwards we said what was I
thinking there we choose things that
could be good but end up being bad
because we don't pay close enough
attention to what we're doing we start
with a good intention but don't follow
through on it or we prioritize things in
a way that that gets in our own way that
hinders us things Epictetus is term or
sometimes we fail to fulfill the duties
that we
and that leads us into action sometimes
when we have an action we don't follow
through on it we don't check up to see
whether the results actually turned out
the way that we assumed or you know
things turn out differently than we
intended because we we don't act in a
pure vacuum we were within an entire
matrix of causes that include other
people and the universe itself and all
of these these processes and so things
go astray and we have to stay on top of
that so those are all different ways in
which we might experience failure and we
might you know when we bring the
stoicism into the mix in a way it kind
of raises the bar so we hold ourselves
to higher standards then we would have
had we would have in the past when it
comes to our choices and actions and
thoughts and particularly to emotions
you know for myself I've struggled my
entire life with anger that's part of
how I got into studies over the first
place so I'm gonna you know the back
story I'm and I'll be happy to share it
in the Q&A if people want and you know
the Stoics are very zero-tolerance when
it comes to ager and I can say I fail at
that probably not every single day but
pretty close and so you know when we we
begin to hold ourselves to higher
standards we become much more conscious
of where we're failing we also do so and
I think this is a very helpful mental
construct when it comes to virtues and
vices you know when we can give a name
to ways in which we don't want to be and
it's bad for a person to be and we can
give a name to the ways that we ought to
be that would be good for us to be that
helps us to guide ourselves and and you
know we often fail when it comes to the
virtues the entire realm of duties or
appropriate actions aphasia in the Latin
our relations to others well we often
fail in those I'll speak for myself I
often those may be some what do you do
as well and stoicism you know reinforces
for us hey you
all these connections to other people
you really need to pay attention to them
and do the right thing in in the fabric
of those relationships and you know you
might say oh well that makes you know in
that case maybe we should get rid of
Stoicism it just makes us more miserable
right it's not fulfilling its promise of
making us happier and you know we might
want to think about the legendary sage
of the fact that maybe some of you aim
to be the sage I don't I'm a Procope Don
and I intend to be that my entire life
because that's good enough you know I
just want to get a bit better and a bit
better just like Epictetus says hey I
don't have to be Socrates it's enough if
I just make some progress along way and
I think another thing that epictetus
says is helpful in this all of you
remember that the passage from the
enchiridion about the beginner blames
everybody except for themselves right
and the person who's making some
progress blames himself and then the
person who's actually made a lot of
progress or understands things doesn't
blame anybody and we use this as a class
of a Qatari principle I think we should
see this as a continuum instead you know
as a process where we wean ourselves
away from blaming other people and we
start focusing more on what we need to
change in ourselves and what we need to
be you know sometimes hard on ourselves
about and then eventually move away from
that as well doesn't mean that we're
ever going to get there
entirely and not blame anybody and be
totally cool with everything that's
going on maybe that's not not what we do
another thing I wanted to talk about is
common mistakes that people make when
they fail and how we can look at them
from the stoic perspective and I think
looking at them from the stoic
perspective will happen more in the Q&A
but here's some common mistakes and you
can add your own as well so the first
one is denying that there was any
failure in the first place right it
didn't happen and then you know all of
you are familiar with them the payoff
well it didn't happen oh it did happen
but I you know wasn't me
was me but I didn't intend it oh I did
intend it but it really didn't have the
bad effect that that you're saying it
that you know all this minimizing that
goes out that is not helpful at all
right
if we fail who we need to actually
acknowledge that we did fail another big
problem that people launch themselves
into a rather set of problems and
actually when I was thinking about this
I realized this is a very common theme
in sitcoms a person will fail at
something and then they will try to fix
it by any means they can and they don't
they don't approach it attentively they
don't approach it with proce okay as we
would say in stoicism they're reacting
immediately and the efforts that they
make make it worse and worse and worse
worse until around the you know 28
minute mark everything falls apart and
then we have a nice you know coming
together and we learned a lesson sort of
thing well you know in real life this is
this approach towards failure often
doesn't pay off that way
shifting responsibilities to others
that's another problematic way of
dealing with failure we actually need to
deal with things that are our business
the things that are up to us ignoring
how we make things harder for others
when we fail that's that's another
common thing as well and I think if
we're Stoics we have to think about
larger systems that were involved so
like you know for example if I didn't
show up until 20 minutes into this I
would be putting out however many people
are I can't I can't tell exactly right
now helmet however many people were
waiting for this right if I let if I
fail myself I let others down sometimes
and that's a matter of justice and a
matter of duties another thing that
often happens when people fail is
excessive emotional reactions and
sometimes this can be you know guilt or
shame sadness is a common one anxiety
you know what if people think I'm a bad
person because of this
some of the other ones that come up that
maybe you don't experience but I know I
do
frustration that leads to anger and then
lashing out at others which generates
yet another failure
or even a desire and enjoyment and
seeing others fail so that least it you
know detracts from from what you're
doing another another common mistake I
think is being too concerned about what
other people will think and not about
what you're actually dealing with in the
situation so how can we approach these
things as a stoic I think one of the
most helpful principles is the dichotomy
of control you know thinking about what
is genuinely up to us and what isn't up
to us and one thing that we definitely
don't control is whether we failed or
not so you know once we fail that is set
and that's there in the past and we can
tell whatever story as we want about it
and we can reframe things in more
productive ways but the thing happened
and if it came from something within us
a failure within us that's still there
too and you know we can change how we
approach it in the future but we really
can't do much more than that
we will have failings and failures with
respect to all sorts of things that are
indifference and you know those in fact
do matter as Epictetus tells us the
things that are in difference like say
money it doesn't have no value
whatsoever it just doesn't have the
value that a lot of people ascribe to it
and how we use it is important and is up
to us so we can think about those those
you know classifications prudence has to
do with how we use indifference in large
part same thing with justice the same
thing with fortitude and we probably
should try to work on our skills and
abilities that we call virtues it will
help us deal well with these
indifference so I think that's one key
thing you know
we look at what is in our control and we
focus on a mat but we also try to
maintain some focus on what we don't
absolutely control but can influence we
should do that well another thing is
being concerned about as I mentioned
what other people make of our failures
and Marcus has a thing that he says at
one point Epictetus I believe has
another thing in Seneca has something
similar where somebody's criticizing
somebody else and they say well
obviously you don't know me that well
because if you did you know not only
would you criticize me for this one
thing over here that I fail that boy
you'd see all these other things where
I'm screwing up as well and doing that
can kinda help you put things in
perspective I'm not saying you can say
that to everybody
but you can sort of say that to yourself
in your mind and then maybe not feel as
as bad about the single thing that is
weighing upon you
realism about success rates is also very
important you know Socrates himself has
that patinas tells us went around and
this is his divine mission in epictetus
--is of you to go around and tell people
focus on your soul don't worry so much
on these other things and what was his
success rate about one in a thousand so
if Socrates himself was not succeeding
all of the time maybe we need to adjust
downward depending on what it is our
conception what success and failure are
maybe some of the things that we think
of as failures partly failures and you
could say well in that case we go back
to the dichotomy of control all Socrates
could do is put the message out there
and you know in a very assertive way
which got him killed eventually but it's
up to the other people to take that into
account and that's not up to him we can
also think about what we learn from
failures as experiences experiences are
appearances fantasy I for christos ISM
which doesn't mean that they have no
reality whatsoever even reason itself
the Faculty of reason
is a system of appearances Epictetus
tells us so we need to look at how
things are connected with each other and
whether we're getting them right
cognitively and effectively the last
thing I would say you know that might be
helpful from a stoic perspective and
this is not just there in stoic advice
but it runs throughout intentional modes
of living is that we can't hope to fix
everything at once if we do here if we
discover failings in ourselves we have
to work on them bit by bit so if I'm you
know struggling to not drink you know
two pots of coffee a day which I'm not
going to change by the way oh that's
that's my normal consumption there's
there's other things I could focus on
more like you know what my students need
for me but if I decided to make that my
focus
I probably shouldn't try to do
everything else at the same time and we
can remind ourselves what is the goal of
stoic philosophy so the stock answers
are you dumb or Nia right good flow of
life and tranquility and how do we
actually do that what does that actually
look like the Stoics tell us this is
where we get to the Nitty Gritty of it
then it means understanding and choosing
and actually doing the things that we're
supposed to do appropriate actions or
duties they also tell us and epictetus
it's like constantly stressing this that
the goal of the stomach life is to
recognize where we are in conflict with
ourselves where we are contradictions
though Greek word for that is my
literally battle where we're fighting
ourselves and to work through that
gradually untangling these knots that we
have within ourselves they also think
that we are truth seeking animals we
want to know reality we don't want to be
screwing up health it's that in our
assessing things so we have to be very
realistic about the world and very
realistic about ourselves that means
seeing where we're we're failing and
stoic philosophy is about a progressive
transformation of the person it's not
about an on/off switch where we learn
some principles and now everything turns
into happiness and
and tranquility instead we have to do
some work so here's where we get to
fortitude and I realize I'm already
going a little bit fine so I'm going to
keep this fairly short so fortitude is a
virtue right
we often translated as courage in Latin
it's fortitude fortitudo and in Greek
it's on delay and like the other for the
other three cardinal virtues
it's an overarching basket of things so
what does it encompass it does include
the traditional notion of like dealing
with fear for anxiety right being brave
in the face of danger or stuff like that
but it encompasses more for the Stoics
so Cicero tells us in on duties that
fear is one of the emotions that it
helps us to handle desire is another and
anger is another as well those all fall
within the scope of this area's didymus
who you know if you haven't checked him
out he's worth he's worth taking a look
at he gave this epitome of stoic ethics
he talks about these five different
aspects to courage or fortitude
so in Greek I'll give you the Greek
terms and I'll tell you what they mean
and I'll give you his gloss on them
because he doesn't go much further than
that
so the first one is car Tyria and this
week we translate his perseverance but
also as endurance depending on which
translation you're looking at and he
calls this the knowledge there they're
all types of knowledge a piston a but
they're not like just purely cognitive
they're also you know with within our
habits and and our feelings this is a
knowledge that that is ready to remain
and what is right been rightly decided
so when we've decided we want to do X
perseverance helps us to do that that's
part of what it means to be courageous
in this respect so being courageous
doesn't have to be running into the
burning building it could be actually
doing the things that you said you were
going to do washing all the dishes
instead of saying we'll do them in the
morgue
you know to take a sort of trivial
example another one that's a little bit
closer to like the the feeling of
courage is that are they old tastes
intrepid Ness it's related to the word
for confidence and he says this is the
knowledge through which we know we will
not encounter anything terrible we can
really realize that we're up to the
challenges in front of us even if they
happen to be you know like dealing with
this terrible illness that's going on
another one that they said fits into
that is McCallum sukhiya which is often
translated as great soul in Nisour
magnanimity Aristotle treats it as a
separate virtue of the Stoics thought
that fit under courage and it's a rising
above it's rising above and sort of
looking at things from that perspective
so it helps us put things into
perspective and he says it doesn't just
apply to trivial stuff it also applies
to the stuff that's genuinely valuable
so we realize that you know it is
valuable for us to have certain
relationships but if we have to let
those go in order to accomplish it a yet
greater good then we do that another one
is what he calls you sophia
stout-hearted miss this is something i
think a lot of people are attracted to
in stoicism its knowledge belonging to
the soul grasping itself is unconquered
reminding ourselves that we do get to
decide we are the ones who determine
what we're going to do with ourselves
and our faculties and our abilities and
then the final one that I particularly
like is called Philip onea literally
meaning loving toil or loving difficult
things and so this is translated as
industrious Nisour diligence it means
being able to accomplish what's proposed
without being prevented by the toil
that's involved and this is where like
you know we get reluctant sometimes we
encounter things or like yeah I've got
this great idea this intention and then
you know it gets kind of late at night
we're tired and like I'll do that later
and then it doesn't happen that's a
failing right and so by being
industrious
we can not just keep ourselves from
doing that but we can return back to
what we need to do Epictetus doesn't
talk about courage much but he does talk
about all these parts he doesn't use the
word virtue very often now becker
himself i think many of you know his new
stoicism he summarizes these in three
things courage endurance and
perseverance but it covers a lot of the
same ground and he says that we need
these in order to be able to exercise
our agency that we ought to have so you
know this I think maybe it's sort of
like a little pep talk more than a deep
analysis or anything like that but it
gives you an idea about how we can use
this this virtue fortitude to approach
the inevitable failing failures that we
we see and then the failings within us
that we want to work on the last thing
I'll say is you know the stomach's are
often portrayed as saying that virtue is
just a kind of knowledge right and
that's true they do think that there's a
cognitive side too it's not just you
know having an automatic response you do
need to know what you're doing and you
do need to think about it and you do
need attentiveness
Epictetus talks about us is having the
virtues within us as sort of resources
that we can draw upon and that's another
aspect to it these are all part of our
nature if we choose to develop it but
the other thing where the Stoics do line
up with other virtue ethicists is their
emphasis on if we want to actually have
the virtues available to us if we want
to have the fortitude we have to
continually choose and practice and that
leads to establishing new habits that is
going to happen over time and there's
sort of a meta level here we're going to
fail at that too and so we have to be
willing to you know if we want to use
more of the imagery like the wrestler
pick himself up dust himself off and get
back in the ring again and fortitude is
the virtue that helps us do that so
fortitude develops itself in its own
practice
the last thing I'll close out I'm just
saying well if you do this it gets
better it gets easier I'm saying that
from somebody who's gone a bit of the
way and can see you know further on the
horizon probably some of you are further
along with that than I am but you know
the message is you can do this you can
deal with failings and failures and it's
okay
it's in one respect it's okay to fail
because you're going to and you have to
become okay with it
obviously you'd want to fail less but
you want to be quite realistic with
yourself about what's going on
so fortitude is the thing that we need
to focus on that that's that's my shape
here so I'll open it up to Q&A cool cool
so if you have any questions write it to
Greg in the chat box and I'll calling
you Tony yourself or I'll read on your
behalf and I'll warm up Greg right now
with the question of my own or me well
I'll share some thoughts and then maybe
we can tease out a question here yeah so
what was salient is when you mentioned
the the sitcom thing because my wife and
I just finished watching the whole
series of friends and I had a Jason
thought similar to that that I noticed
everyone freaking lies in every episode
they're lying
same thing with signs are always lying
and you're right the lying stems from
some minor mistake or failure or
whatever and then they make it worse by
lying right and if they were just being
upfront and forthright and truthful then
there wouldn't be an episode essentially
and what comes to mind is that Jordan
Hall had his take on wisdom is being in
right relationship with reality which
could do another spin of like living in
accordance with nature and so the
thought came to mind like what is right
relationship with failure you know
similar what you're talking about so I
just throw that out you if you think
that's a helpful framework if anything
came to mind yeah and as I mentioned you
know the Stoics think of us as animals
that have these sort of basic drives
towards things and unlike the other ones
we have a drive towards truth and that's
where the the virtual wisdom gets its
beginnings from according to Cicero
who's just you know essentially telling
us what Cato said so
kind of
Orthodox stoic teaching in that case and
and I think that's completely right we
want to have a vertical relationship
with reality and we're part of reality
so we want to understand ourselves and
sometimes part of so sometimes I can be
a very painful truth to see right you
know oh I thought I had all my hangers
stuff done and then we start you know
talking about recipes and somehow we get
into you know shouting at each other or
something like yeah well there's a sign
that things are not as I thought they
were you know it's kind of funny with
the sitcom thing as you're attacking
about that we were fans of Curb Your
Enthusiasm and Larry David is like he's
an epitome of this he's sort of a you
know he's kind of stoic about stuff with
a lowercase s it doesn't matter right
but he's constantly screwing things up
worse and worse worse by making a bad
decision and then trying to cover it up
in some way yeah you know the notion
that we could somehow fix things by
lying okay that's a false thing right so
being wise would be realizing among
other things realizing that you can't
fix things just by telling people some
sort of story to mollify them but you
you have to fix the relationship so now
and that's probably you know in some
respects too messy and boring to make
good TV yeah so we'll flip it to the
questions and thus I would like me to
read this so how do you apply this view
to the failures versus failings of other
people seems a relevant aspect in a time
when many are eager to criticize others
reactions or lack of reaction in the
face of crisis yeah that's that's a
great question and so we can talk about
that in a number of different ways you
know we can talk about how one one
interprets it oneself and whether you
know whether you're doing the right
thing you could say in relation to other
people's failings which most of the time
is going to be not talking about them
ignoring them because it's not your
business you know I get on Twitter and
Twitter is kind of
a great place for everybody getting up
in each other's business because you
know even the people the people who you
follow are bringing other people into
your stream and there might be a
temptation to correct people or I'll say
oh you're totally mistaken about this
this sort of thing and I think as a
stoic you would you would want to think
well is it really worth my time to get
involved in this particular situation
this particular tip now if we're talking
about people closer to us maybe those
who we have responsibility for so like
you know if my kids are doing something
that's not to their benefit or might be
harming others I probably should say
something to them about that and maybe
even if I have any any sway in the
situation because you know quite often
kids are you know they really are their
own thing their own little world try to
influence them and bring them towards
what's good and we could say this maybe
you know you think about this I hadn't
thought about this before but you know
think about the concentric circles that
we talked about with here achlys and we
usually bring this up in terms of Winkie
OSIS and you know like loving everybody
ultimately out to the ends of the earth
and all the human you know but but
there's also that that more inner circle
where we are more concerned with them
and we probably in times like this
probably should pay closer attention I
need to focus for example on my students
I don't need to really worry about what
my Dean is doing even if the policies
that they're they're doing seem a little
bit counterproductive I need to focus
more on my tasks there will be some
people's failures that are going to be
bad in many respects for other people
and you know the most we can do often is
a day or screwing up here would be a
better path but you know right now well
so we you know let's talk about the
colvett 19 crisis
most countries have some sort of unified
response at this point in time here in
the United States we don't it's been
left up to the individual state it's and
some of the individual states left it up
to individual municipalities and so you
know there have been some very imprudent
decisions made in recent times and we're
going to suffer the consequences for
them and you know strictly speaking
these have to do with what the Stoics
would call a difference you know being
healthier sick wealthy you know we're
looking at economic collapse in many
cases or poorer
but indifference do matter and we we
shouldn't just you know say hello or
stomachs so why is it doesn't affect my
own virtue or advice you know I think
it's okay to be critical in adequate
responses but you know here we can talk
about man or how do we do that
do we allow ourselves to get all angry
and worked up about it do we start
calling people names how you know how do
we do it you know
sonica himself this is a bit of a side
note says that in some cases even though
you're not angry it could be useful to
look angry if you're dealing with people
who only understand that that point of
view he talks about a judge displaying
anger towards a a criminal defendant and
you know maybe our legislators only get
you know when we seem upset with them
but that doesn't mean that we actually
have to be himself so that's kind of a
long-winded answer so next question and
just a disclaimer other questions we
might not get to all the questions and
I'm not gonna be reading an order I'm
gonna use my discernment to kind of like
yes and the previous thing Greg said so
uh Alex so you have a question for Greg
would you like to go off from you and
ask it
[Music]
Alex I'll unmute you if you like yeah
you're unmuted
okay thanks Peter thanks for your
presentation I was wondering about fear
and Stroke and stoicism and the virtue
of courage specifically I guess I'm
wondering what happens when a person
acts courageously the sphere disappear
completely or is it just somehow
transformed and managed you know just
puts it under our control because I've
read I've read that for the Stoics you
know like the stoic sage lives without
any fear at all and I know for somebody
like Aristotle you know fear is always
going to be there and it's just a matter
of kind of managing it well so yes for
Aristotle this that's not actually the
case
and Aristotle's closer to the Stoics on
this Aristotle says that the courageous
person will feel fear in the face of
things that are genuinely fearful but
they're not going to feel fear when they
when it doesn't make sense to feel it
the way somebody who say has a phobia
does right so you know if you're if
you're in the Mediterranean in the
ancient world on a ship and you're in
the middle of a storm and you and your
the the poor guy who's got to go up a
Bob and like secure the things that are
otherwise going to move around that
makes sense to be scared okay
but you master you try to master the
fear and not allow it to dominate you so
you can do the right thing and the
Stoics have a similar thing so in some
cases it will mean not feeling fear and
this is where the cognitive side comes
in if you understand that some things
aren't really scary even though people
say that they are or your first reaction
is to think that they are you can you
can avoid feeling fear but even even
though the stomach philosophy or we will
talk about sages but even the stoic
philosopher is gonna handle these these
free emotions where the body just kind
of you know reacts to things maybe the
adrenaline starts flowing and a man
but there will be some things that will
be genuinely scary and this is where I
guess I'm tempted to think that modern
stoicism would acknowledge a wider range
of the Stoics had with what are called
you pave right the good emotions the
good emotional states and caution you LA
baya is one of those and that's feeling
fear when it's rational to feel fear I
think maybe we would be a little bit
more wide in our scope so you know for
example my kids are down in Indiana
right now they're they're separated from
from me by two states and I know that
they're doing okay living out in the
countryside but I can still feel some
concern for them and now does that have
to look rise to the level of something
where I'm calling them up all the time
vortex how are you doing you're not
you're not coughing or yet or anything
like that right no itch that that would
be clearly off base but exhibiting what
the Stoics called caution you know that
does make sense in a lot of cases and
you know so if we let's think of very
practical terms we live in an apartment
complex here and I have a wife who's
immune compromised we have quite a few
younger people living in the complex who
seemed rather cavalier about contagion
and social distancing and things like
that and you know we have to be careful
we have to be cautious about that
[Music]
and so there will be some things where
you know somebody wants to get on the
elevator with me my reaction is don't
take the next elevator buddy you know
and it may seem kind of rude and I can
do that without feeling you know oh this
things to think gripping me this fear
and my gut but it but it is still within
the same affective domain and if I see
somebody doing something really dumb you
know like I don't licking the elevator
buttons I should I should feel some
sense of you know like the hairs on my
at the back of my neck could wake up
something goes really wrong there that's
kind of silly an example but if you get
what I'm saying all right so so there's
there's kind of a complex spectrum you
could say in some cases it's going to
keep you from feeling fear at all
because you've realized this isn't
really something scary in other cases it
will be though the more it seems more
Aristotelian but it is also equally
stoic to work despite the fact that
you're feeling fear so Ben had a
question he'd like me to read it for him
how does the stoic concept of fortitude
relate to or differ from modern notions
of resilience and anti fragility I would
say there's a lot of overlap there the
notion of resilience is is one of those
things where you ask you know ten
experts and you get ten different
answers about what exactly a consistent
so I think we'd have to pin down what
what a person precisely means by it I
think it covers a lot of the same ground
since what we're talking about here is
perseverance and industriousness and
maybe some of what they they called you
know the Michalek sukiya or you know
being able to rise above things because
that means being able to put things in
in perspective the antifragility thing
is kind of an interesting take to think
about particularly in terms of the how
we was you know how we bounce back from
failure right so anti fragile things
aren't perfect and they're not like
armored against everything else but and
they and they take some damage and
sometimes even real trauma but they're
able to
you know sort of self organize and
reorganize in ways that then make them
stronger as a result and so with with
that describe what a stoic courageous
response would be when you actually fail
I think it probably would so I think
that could be a helpful helpful
criterion are we making ourselves more
as persons more anti fragile by the way
in which we're approaching our failures
I mean the opposite would be oh I failed
on everything's everything's doom and
gloom I'll never be able to like show my
face or do anything again that's that's
you know not just a lack of resiliency
that's also being gradual right you're
completely shattered and you know it's
it's interesting that you ask that too
because you know we're going to come
back from this crisis and things are
going to be changed in so many ways some
of them for the worse some of them for
the better and it's going to be in
response to what we go through
I mean we're you know the more more
pessimistic predictions are we're only
in the very beginning of our self
quarantine and social isolation and
stuff like that we might be going on for
months and months and months and you
know the economy is going to look quite
different when we're when we're finished
with this there's going to be a lot of
you know my wife has a lot of
connections in the food and restaurant
industry they're really hurting right
now you know a lot of restaurants are
going to go under and what's going to be
left after we're done we'll have to see
how how the whole industry is able to
bounce back and then we say that whole
industry I mean all these other people
whose livelihoods are dependent upon it
many people it's their entry-level jobs
so you know I guess we'll see which
systems are actually anti fragile as
well
stoic Dan and you had a question feel
free to unmute yourself oh I think I
might have to yeah yeah you can unmute
yourself now dan great thank you
um earlier in your talk Greg you
mentioned that Stoics have a zero
tolerance to anger and that's usually
the way I would describe it as well but
just yesterday I was listening to
Massimo talk on another call like this
and he said that sometimes a stoic will
need to show anger to snap someone into
doing the right thing kind of like that
rare oddity that we sometimes hear about
a buddhist teacher slapping his student
so oh but massimo added that you should
not feel anger inside you should only
display it and this should be rare what
do you think about that that's exactly
what Seneca said that's that's the
example in on anger of the judge who
appears to be angry so displays you know
they don't display anger in the sense of
acting from anger within them they
display the conventional appearance of
anger like raising their voice and you
know maybe like they make themself get
red in the face or something like that
we can imagine so that's you know that's
pretty straightforward there is actually
a debate about going on right now
well maybe the aristotelian who the
Stoics by the way misrepresented I'll
mention as well if we look at that the
ancient you know tanks and stuff like
that a little bit on that this but maybe
they were civilians were a bit right in
thinking that anger would be needed to
galvanize people to doing what's right
you know on a larger scale in terms of
getting our politicians to take the
dangers to working-class people and I
mean here's a great example here in
Milwaukee we've had ten deaths now and
all of them have been on the north side
of Milwaukee at the poor neighborhoods
so there's clearly you know some things
that need to be attended to and I think
it you know could anger get the
politicians to pay more attention to
public health things yeah the problem is
that when we use anger for activism like
like Seneca and Aristotle point out
anger gets away from you really easily
it's kind of a blunt instrument and so
Seneca says anything that we could
accomplish with anger we could
accomplish just by following bright
practical reasoning and so you know
whether or not we can get mass movements
going without it I don't know we can
certainly as individuals act
appropriately without using anger so if
I see my child being bullied anger could
spur me to take a stand against that but
it could also lead me to like you know
going over and punching the bullying
kids dad in the face or something like
that and we don't want those sorts of
excessive reaction so anger is anger is
always kind of dangerous even if we
think a little bit could be okay if we
want to use that beam we can have a
little bit of anger as a treat sometime
no you know it's still kind of kind of
dangerous to do it okay so we have time
for one more question okay let's do this
one so this is from Greg Lopez our
friend from New York so epictetus asked
us to transfer aversions from external
x' to our internal state what's the
balance of blaming yourself without also
inflaming secondary passions about how
you have a failing can you give an
example of how you do it okay that's
that's a good one and and yeah I think
he does in the enchiridion suggests
transferring aversions entirely from
from externals I think some of the stuff
that he says in the discourse is
modifies that but let's say that we're
actually doing this so we're trying to
focus entirely inward on our own and we
couldn't look at it as failings right so
we should be averse to being unless
let's use it in terms of the virtuous
right let's say we're we
realize that we're a little greedy and
that means that we want to take more
than our fair share of things which then
leaves other people in the lurch it
could be like toilet paper for example
right Hawaiian hurting in this crisis I
don't know if that's been happening in
Canada but it's a big problem here in
the States for some reason it's an only
crisis where we've actually seen this
this weird behavior with toilet paper so
you know you you you realize that you're
getting caught up in the hysteria about
how we better get out and get as many
rolls as possible
now you instead of being averse to not
having toilet paper
if we're following you know potatoes
they'd be averse to being the kind of
jerk who goes out and and takes what
other people need and hoards it up and
then now that would require us to like
look at me what's going on with me
what's wrong with me that I do this sort
of thing and now we start to carry out
some analysis and so there's you know
what's going to help us doing that is it
like you know beating our breasts and
say may I cold but no that's that's not
particularly productive as a matter of
fact some people do that sort of thing
precisely so they don't have to engage
in self analysis they feel like they've
gotten himself off of the you know the
the charge that they were involved in
before we'd have to actually look well
why am I so concerned about having this
one commodity what am I afraid of what
am I being averse to so now we're
engaging in introspection and we're
using sort of stoic categories to do
that now how would we avoid not blaming
ourselves in other ways there's a
blaming yourself like getting yourself
off the hook for doing that which is
just a show but what about actually
feeling oh I'm a really bad person for
doing this that's not going to be
particularly productive either how do we
how do we avoid that we could say to or
sell things like well you know I I
screwed up and my screwing up makes
sense given the things that I know about
myself it's not a good thing for me to
do this and I
to move away from this but I don't have
to like you know self lacerate in order
to to get past this or there might be
other emotions to like anger directed at
other people and all those those other
people who made me do this no the other
people didn't make you do that you you
know you have a prior ASIS you have your
own faculty of choice you decided to
allow yourself to get caught up in the
toilet paper hoarding hysteria so can I
give an example of how I do it I mean
hopefully the toilet paper one gives an
example but and could we think about
other ways that aren't quite so silly
that we can do this and other secondary
passions
you know maybe so one interesting one
and this is where we move to where
stoicism and existentialism could
overlap if you think about anxiety the
way that existentialist interpret
anxiety in many cases is a an awareness
of our own freedom that realizes that we
could screw up we could screw up in ways
that would be catastrophic and
Kierkegaard has the example of the guy
who stands at the edge of the cliff and
feels anxiety he knows he's not going to
throw himself off because it would be
stupid to do but you never know maybe
maybe I would do that sort of thing
right and I don't think that Stoics
would be immune to that we are conscious
of our own freedom but if we understand
that dynamic there and we recognize the
emotions as they're coming up and and
what they involve the cognitive
judgments that they they imply we can
sort of short-circuit them and they
won't go away entirely most likely I
don't they don't for me but we can keep
them from having the deciding voice and
what's going to happen so they're not
they're not influencing the pro' a
racist the Faculty of choice or the
ruling principle if you like you know
the other term for that hegemony cone
does that that address it's officially a
thinker or not greg did you want to
respond to that Greg look guys just
might indicate on the chat or go off
mute if not then we will end here so
yeah in a moment I'll do some closing
announcements but I thought yeah I'll
just say this that if you want to
practice your stoicism this is this
place of the Stowe is not going to
always be a place to kind of like
inquire into stone but we're gonna try
to develop an ecology of practices where
we can kind of like build this muscle of
fortitude and this is a collective we're
gonna source the collective intelligence
to do this so if you have any ideas let
us know let me know so before I make
some closing announcements Greg do you
have any closing thoughts of what you're
doing now where people can find you oh
well you know as I said I'm on Twitter
as philosopher 70 and you know obviously
my youtube channel just Google and it'll
it'll pop right up reason IO is just
reason IO calm and I do have you know a
few other things here and there and then
I would say I am editor of Stoicism
today there's a lot of a lot of great
articles that we're having coming in by
guest authors so modern stoicism coms
where that's that's cited otherwise I
mean and I think what you're doing here
is a really great idea I actually have
I'll talk with you later I've got a few
suggestions about people you might have
to bring into it and yeah I don't have
much more to say very cool and I put all
that information of where to find more
about Greg in the chatbox now make some
announcement about upcoming events but
Greg thank you my friend for coming in
today that was a very welcome and thanks
everyone for being on the call and
giving the excellent questions that you
gave so we have a bunch of events I
think we have like 16 lined up you can
go on the website
[Music]
today we have one at 7:00 p.m. Eastern
Time it's called the foreshadowing watch
party so this animator called Luba mere
hours off he did this really excellent
piece called in shadow it has like a
foreshadowing element to what's
happening right now so we're gonna watch
that and then we're gonna together and
then we're gonna have an inquiry so if
you're interested checking that just go
to the website and RSVP there lastly I'm
viewing the stoah as a gift for all of
us to freely use in this time of need if
you're inspired to give a gift in return
just go to the website and go to the
gift economy section at the bottom and
there's more information there all right
thanks everyone